PAUL JAY: Welcome to The Real News Network.
I'm Paul Jay. And welcome to Reality Asserts
Itself.
John Kiriakou is in his house waiting for
another 40 days before he's free to walk out
the front door. He's under house arrest after
spending 23 months in jail.
John Kiriakou was born on August 9, 1964.
He's a former CIA analyst and case officer,
a former senior investigator for the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee, and a former
counterterrorism consultant for ABC News.
He was the first U.S. government official
to confirm in December 2007 that waterboarding
was used to interrogate al-Qaeda prisoners,
which he described as torture. On October
22, 2012, Kiriakou pleaded guilty to disclosing
classified information about a fellow CIA
officer that connected the covert operative
to a specific operation. He was the first
person to pass classified information to a
reporter, although the reporter did not publish
the name of the operative. He was sentenced
to 30 months in prison on January 25, 2013,
and he served his term from February 28, 2013,
until 3 February 2015 at a low-security federal
correctional facility in Loretto, Pennsylvania.
When John joined the CIA in 1990, he was 25
years old. He was a true believer in Americanism--American
exceptionalism, as some people call it. And
now he's not. And that's what this interview's
about.
And now John joins us.
Thank you very much.
JOHN C. KIRIAKOU: Thanks for having me.
JAY: So we're going to do many segments of
this interview, because you've lived a lot
of different lives in the CIA. And, I think,
just to establish the ground rules, some of
what we're going to ask John is classified.
And I'm going to not--not not ask him: I'm
going to ask him whatever we feel like asking
him, and then he's going to figure out if
there's times he has to say, well, I can't
say that, because it's classified, and then
he'll parse what he can say. But just to let
you know, that's going to happen once in a
while--but probably not at the beginning,
'cause I don't think any of you growing up
is classified.
KIRIAKOU: No.
JAY: So, in the beginning we want to talk
about how you become Americanized and how
much that's part of your personal identity.
So your parents are Greek.
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
JAY: You're of Greek origin.
JAY: And when does your family come to the
United States?
KIRIAKOU: My mother's parents came--I should
say, my father's parents came in February
1931, and my mother's parents followed three
years later.
Growing up, to hear my grandfather tell the
story, Franklin Roosevelt personally allowed
him in the country, got him a job in a steel
mill in Canonsburg, Pennsylvania, and by God
we were going to be Democrats for the rest
of our lives to repay the kindness that Franklin
Roosevelt showed. In fact, into the 1970s,
until my grandfather's death in 1978, he had
a framed photo of Franklin Roosevelt sitting
on top of the television set.
So I always grew up with a feeling that I
had to repay the kindness that the country
had shown my family, that we had a debt to
the Democratic Party, specifically to Franklin
Roosevelt, and that public service was something
to which I should aspire.
JAY: And what did your father and mother do?
KIRIAKOU: My dad was an elementary school
principal for 42 years, and my mother was
a third grade teacher.
JAY: And they sort of internalized all this
FDR and America adoration.
KIRIAKOU: Oh, yes, yeah, very much so. Very
much so. Even as a child, I was active politically
because my parents were. Even as an eight-year-old,
a nine-year-old, I was a--it was even earlier
than that, an eight-year-old--I was a volunteer
on the McGovern campaign, stuffing envelopes
and such. And then, even when I went to college,
the first thing I did, literally on my first
day in college, was to join the College Democrats.
JAY: And after Roosevelt, we have Truman.
Did that loyalty transfer on, president to
president? In other words, did you grow up
with the narrative that dropping the bomb
on Hiroshima and Nagasaki was somehow for
the greater good?
KIRIAKOU: I remember a relative of mine saying
Truman taught the Japs a thing or two. And
I'll add, too, that there was at least as
much love for Harry Truman as there was for
Franklin Roosevelt in our family because it
was Truman that saved Greece from communism.
And my grandparents were very grateful for
that.
JAY: And much of Greece was procommunist.
So where did your father, coming in the '30s,
where did they get their anticommunism from?
KIRIAKOU: Well, my grandfather was a voracious
consumer of news, which was hard to do in
the early 1940s. But still he consumed as
much news about Greece as he could, whether
it was from Life magazine or Time magazine--copies
of which I still have, as a matter fact, that
mention Greece, or letters to and from relatives
in Greece. He really stayed up on what was
going on. He was also a member of two Greek-American
organizations--the American Hellenic Educational
Progressive Association (AHEPA) and GAPA (the
Greek American Progressive Association). Both--well,
I should say GAPA was really a liberal group,
but it supported using Greek, the Greek language,
in the home. And AHEPA was more pan-political,
but encouraged newly arrived Greeks to assimilate
and to become Americans and to speak English
in the home. My grandfather was a member of
both organizations.
JAY: Because Roosevelt worked with the Soviet
Union against Hitler,--
KIRIAKOU: For many years.
JAY: --Roosevelt's vice president, Wallace,
if he had been able to stay on as vice president
(he got dumped by the party in favor of Truman),
was very much for working with the Soviet
Union, was against this kind of beginning
of a cold war. So, like, moving from Roosevelt
to Truman is not a natural progression in
terms of--especially when it comes to Greece,
because when you say save Greece from communism,
it was by installing dictators in Greece;
it was not, like, some democracy [incompr.]
KIRIAKOU: But there was even some disagreement
in the home. My grandmother was very conservative.
And although she was a Democrat (she became
a Democrat when she became a citizen), she
was a lifelong royalist when it came to Greek
politics.
JAY: But was she from the working class or
not?
KIRIAKOU: Oh, yes, very much so, very much
so. Her mother died at a young age, and her
father believed that his three daughters should
have a trade, have an education. My grandmother
was the only one of her sisters that went
to school and became a teacher and then a
translator for the Italian occupation government.
She taught Italian soldiers to speak Greek.
Her sisters were a dressmaker and--oh, her
youngest sister ended up owning a gas station
and a butcher shop. So there was always this
drive to succeed, even though they were women,
that my great-grandfather had instilled.
JAY: So, in the narrative of your families,
when it comes to Greece: that the installation
of a dictatorship somehow was a good thing,
and somehow that's for democracy.
KIRIAKOU: It depended on the dictatorship.
My grandparents were really worried about
communism in Greece in the 1940s because the
communists were killing a lot of innocent
people. They would go into villages to recruit
men, and any man that didn't want to go back
up into the mountains to fight for the Greeks
was killed. And oftentimes the wives and children
were killed as well.
JAY: Well, I'm not going to argue with you
about it, but I've interviewed Greek communists
who fought the Nazis and then fought afterwards,
and you get quite a different story.
KIRIAKOU: Sure. Oh, of course you do. And
still, these three generations later, you're
still going to get arguments on both sides.
JAY: Yeah. But at any rate, this is part of
your formation.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah.
JAY: America fights for the greater good.
And as I've said on The Real News a few times,
it's sort of like, we do bad things, but for
good reasons.
KIRIAKOU: Right. I believed that for many
years, decades. And I don't believe that anymore.
JAY: So when we get to you in the high school--so
you're born in '64. The Vietnam War's ending
as you kind of start becoming much more conscious
of politics.
KIRIAKOU: That's right.
JAY: As you head into college, what's your
vision of the world and your place in it,
what you might be doing?
KIRIAKOU: I considered myself at the time
to be what was then called a social democrat--liberal
on social issues, economic issues, and then
pretty hawkish on foreign policy and defense.
I remember there being in retrospect a very
funny debate within the College Democrats
at GW over the invasion of Grenada: should
we issue a statement condemning the invasion
of Grenada? These are, like, six college freshmen
and sophomores debating whether we should
issue a statement like anybody cared. And
I remember opposing a statement, because I
supported the invasion of Grenada. I don't
recall why, but I did. I felt, I guess, that
it showed a robust foreign policy and it showed
that we were willing to go out and protect
our citizens.
JAY: We needed a win.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, we needed a win. It had been
a while since we had had a win. But all through
college I was pretty hawkish on foreign policy
issues.
JAY: But you were also--excuse me--in a little
bit weird way, very interested in politics
and leaders.
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
JAY: Didn't you at some point write a letter
to the Shah, and you got a signed, autographed
picture back? What was that all about?
KIRIAKOU: I think I was 14 or 15. I wrote
a letter to the Shah of Iran, and I wrote
to tell him that I was disgusted by the way
our government had treated him, that once
we had made a decision, we should have stuck
with the decision, and the decision had been
to allow him to come to the United States
for treatment of his cancer. And when the
heat got a little more than the president
could handle, the Shah was unceremoniously
thrown out and ended up in Panama, and then,
later, the Bahamas. So I wrote him a letter
saying, it's terrible the way you were treated.
And he actually wrote me a letter back saying,
you're right, it's terrible the way I've been
treated; here's an autographed picture.
JAY: He probably didn't get many letters like
that.
KIRIAKOU: No, I'm sure he didn't.
JAY: What motivated you?
KIRIAKOU: I don't know. I was just so interested
in foreign affairs that it just seemed like
a natural thing to do.
I followed the Iran hostage crisis day by
day by day, for example. And even though Nightline
was on very late at night for a 14-year-old
or 15-year-old, I stayed up every single night
and watched Ted Koppel on Nightline, because
originally Nightline was to give us a daily
update of events in Iran.
JAY: Yeah, they'd have a day count, every
day, with so many days more and the hostages.
Yeah.
KIRIAKOU: That's right. And so I was just
fascinated by it.
And I remember telling my father--we were
in the car together. And my dad, for whatever
reason, always wanted me to become a dentist.
And I remember telling him, Dad, I really
don't want to be a dentist. And he said, well,
what do you want to do? And I said, I think
I want to join the foreign service.
JAY: This is at 14.
KIRIAKOU: I was 14, I guess, at the time.
And he said, well, whatever you want to do,
just do it well.
JAY: And you wrote Margaret Thatcher.
KIRIAKOU: I did.
JAY: But your choice of leaders are all kind
of the--.
KIRIAKOU: They were very conservative.
JAY: Very conservative.
KIRIAKOU: They were very conservative. I got
an autographed picture from Ezer Weizman,
at the time the defense minister of Israel.
These are people that today I wouldn't dream
of writing a letter of support to, but back
then I was pretty hawkish.
JAY: Was there anyone influencing you in this
direction? Or was it kind of just your own
thing?
KIRIAKOU: No, no. It was just--it was my own
thing. It was my own interest.
JAY: So you go to college.
KIRIAKOU: Uh-huh.
JAY: And what do you study?
KIRIAKOU: Middle Eastern studies.
JAY: Why?
KIRIAKOU: I don't know. I was fascinated with
the Middle East.
A couple of people asked me if I was interested
in Hellenic studies. I could have studied
at Georgetown or--I mean, there are several
different places that you can study Hellenic
studies, good schools. And I said, no, I was
more interested in the Middle East. And then
my dad, in an attempt to get me to stay close
to home, said, well, you know, the University
of Pittsburgh has a great Eastern European
studies program. And I said, I don't care
about Eastern European studies, I don't care
about the Soviet Union. I truly didn't. I
only cared about the Middle East. And there
were three schools in the country at the time
that had Middle Eastern studies programs:
George Washington, Rutgers, and Brigham Young.
And George Washington was the easy choice.
JAY: Now, as [you get] into the late '70s,
even the early '80s, you're coming to consciousness,
you know, political, you're interested in
foreign affairs. How does--is the revelations
of what really happened in Vietnam and what
a lie--mostly lies that the war was based
on--yeah, there's quotes from senior Johnson
officials near the end of the war that if
70 percent of the reason we're in Vietnam
is just to prove how strong we are, it's now
become 100 percent of the reason for being
in Vietnam. And you hear that under Nixon,
that it became just about proving to the world
we can't lose a war, meaning tens of thousands
of lives--I mean, really, millions of lives,
including perhaps at least 3 million Vietnamese,
Cambodians, and thousands of American soldiers.
Does that not in some way start to shake your
Americanism?
KIRIAKOU: Not at first. In fact, I haven't
thought about this in years, but I remember
an argument that I got into with a friend
of mine in the College Democrats over Vietnam,
and I said that I had opposed the war--not
had opposed--I opposed the war. I thought
it was immoral. I thought it was illegal.
But if I had been drafted, I would have gone.
And he said if he had been drafted, he would
have gone to Canada. And we had a real argument
about that. And he said to me, how can you
oppose a war and then go fight in it? And
I said, because my country asked me to. I
wouldn't give that same answer today, but
as an 18-year-old that's what I believed.
JAY: But you did think it was immoral and
illegal,--
KIRIAKOU: I did.
JAY: --'cause a lot of the leaders you're
writing to and so on, I mean, they would have
not said so.
KIRIAKOU: In fact, I introduced George McGovern
when he announced his candidacy for president
in September 1984.
JAY: Yeah, I saw that.
KIRIAKOU: And in my speech of introduction,
I said that he was one of the few senators
to stand up to the illegal and immoral war
in Vietnam.
JAY: That seems a little contradictory with
all the other positions you were taking and
supporting Grenada.
KIRIAKOU: When I was a kid, 19 at the time.
Yeah.
JAY: You were still figuring it out.
KIRIAKOU: Still figuring it out. We used to
go to the White House at night when you could
walk right up to the gate and shout--can I
swear on this program?
JAY: Oh, yes, you can.
KIRIAKOU: And shout, "Fuck you, Reagan!" you
know, based on something we had seen on the
news that night.
JAY: But you supported the invasion of Grenada.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, I know.
JAY: So what were you--.
KIRIAKOU: I yelled "Fuck you, Reagan" at the
fence, and then I'd go back to the College
Democrats and say, you know, guys, I've got
to go with Reagan on this one.
JAY: But still the underlying thing is America
can really do no wrong--maybe mistakes, maybe
errors.
KIRIAKOU: That's exactly how I felt. Sure,
we made mistakes, certainly, but our hearts
were in the right place.
I really believed that we were that shining
city on a hill. Back then and for many years
later, really until September 11, I believed
that.
JAY: Well, we're going to get to that.
In the continuation of our series of interview
with John, we're going to ask him how he got
recruited into the CIA.
Please join us for the next in our series
of interviews on Reality Asserts Itself on
The Real News Network.